How are you? Please,
Guten Tag. Bitte.
What’s your name? REPORTER: My name is David [Cooper?], I am (inaudible)
Wie ist Ihr Name? Mein Name ist David [Cooper?].
Can You tell me why You have come along
Können Sie mir sagen, warum Sie diese Woche
to Northampton here this week?
hierher nach Northhampton gekommen sind?
SHRI MATAJI: Why I have come here?
Warum Ich hier bin?
REPORTER: Why You have come along here were you invited by a....
Warum sind Sie gekommen? Wurden Sie eingeladen?
SHRI MATAJI: It’s a sort of a… kind of a message I have,
Ich habe eine Art Botschaft,
that a discovery has been made now of a method.
zu einer Technik, die jetzt entdeckt wurde.
REPORTER: Is this the first time that You’ve come to Northampton?
Sind Sie zum ersten Mal in Northampton?
SHRI MATAJI: No, I’ve come before also.
Nein, Ich war schon einmal hier.
REPORTER: And what sort of response did You get then?
Und wie waren damals die Reaktionen?
SHRI MATAJI: Response was, I wouldn’t say very good.
Die Resonanz war nicht sehr gut.
No newspaper didn’t come at all.
Keine einzige Zeitung berichtete darüber.
Yesterday also there was no one, it’s very surprising.
Auch gestern kam niemand. Es ist sehr erstaunlich.
REPORTER: You found a lot of people were very skeptical, did You?
Sie sahen, dass viele Leute sehr skeptisch waren, nicht wahr?
SHRI MATAJI: I don’t know what they were like,
Ich weiß nicht, wie sie waren,
because no-, nobody came, you see.
weil niemand kam.
REPORTER: That was the Guild Hall as well?
War das auch in der Guildhall?
SHRI MATAJI: No, Guildhall yesterday we had lots of people, yesterday.
Nein, in der Guildhall waren gestern sehr viele Menschen.
But as far as the newspapers were concerned,
Aber was die Zeitungen betrifft,
We met some people here.
waren nur wenige Leute hier.
But most of them came to see Me, when I came here first.
Die meisten waren gekommen, als Ich zum ersten Mal hier war.
They were sort of a labor class people.
Es waren Leute aus der Arbeiterklasse.
They were suffering from all kinds of maladies
Sie hatten alle möglichen Krankheiten,
like possessions and things, and one gentleman just got up
durch Besetzungen usw., ein Mann stand einfach auf
and started walking all around the places and talking like …
und begann herumzulaufen und zu reden wie ein...
it was a bit funny.
Es war ein bisschen komisch.
REPORTER: In fact, You were in Bedford last night, weren't You?
Gestern Abend waren Sie in Bedford, ja?
SHRI MATAJI: Yes, I was there.
Ja, Ich war da.
REPORTER: And how did that go?
Und wie war es?
SHRI MATAJI: Very good, very well.
Sehr gut.
REPORTER: It went very well. In the past, I understand, that You’ve, um,
Ich habe gehört, Sie haben
You’ve helped heal an awful lot of people? SHRI MATAJI: Yes.
schon sehr viele Menschen geheilt. Ja.
REPORTER: Can You give me some examples of some of the more,
Können Sie mir Beispiele für besondere Fälle,
extraordinary healings You’ve done?
die Sie geheilt haben?
SHRI MATAJI: Anything, you see, like cancer.
Alle mögliche. Krebs zum Beispiel.
Then, we can say, blood cancer specially.
Insbesondere auch Blutkrebs.
A Sahaja Yogini has cured one friend's blood cancer.
Eine Sahaja Yogini hat einen Freund von Blutkrebs geheilt.
Then diabetes.
Dann Diabetes.
REPORTER: In fact, I understand, on one occasion You had
Ich habe auch gehört, dass einmal
a blind woman cometo see you, is that right?
eine blinde Frau zu Ihnen gekommen ist. Stimmt das?
SHRI MATAJI: Yes, blindness — if the eyes are open.
Ja, Blindheit - wenn die Augen offen sind.
REPORTER: Which one was that exactly? What was happening?
Wie war das? Was ist passiert?
SHRI MATAJI: That is due to a possession, on the backside,
Es kommt von einer Besetzung auf dem Hinterkopf,
the optic lobe we have here.
hier ist der für das Sehen zuständige Hirnlappen.
You see, if that gets possessed by a live entity,
Wenn es von einer lebenden Entität besetzt wird,
your eyes are open but there’s darkness, you can’t see anything.
dann sind die Augen offen, aber es ist dunkel und man sieht nichts.
And if you know how to open that and get rid of the possession…
Wenn man weiß, wie man es öffnet und die Besessenheit beseitigt...
And the deaf person hearing, yeah…
Auch Taube können dann hören.
REPORTER: You’ve actually cured deafness as well, have You?
Sie haben auch Taubheit geheilt?
SHRI MATAJI: Yes, I did. There in Geneva it happened.
Ja, das war in Genf.
REPORTER: Do You — I mean, it’s very difficult for people
Es ist doch sehr schwierig für die Leute,
to actually understand how it’s done.
zu verstehen, wie das geht.
I mean they, you know, it all seems just a bit mystical and, you know …
Das alles wirkt doch sehr mystisch.
SHRI MATAJI: Yeah. It is nothing mystical, I tell you,
Das ist alles überhaupt nicht mystisch,
there’s nothing mystical.
es ist nicht mystisch.
Like we see a flower becoming a fruit.
Wenn wir sehen, wie eine Blüte zur Frucht wird,
We take it for granted, isn’t it?
dann halten wir das für selbstverständlich, oder?
Do we find it mystical ? Because we see it every day.
Finden wir es mystisch? Wir sehen es eben jeden Tag.
But there is something, some power that does that, doesn’t it?
Aber da muss doch etwas sein, eine Kraft, die das tut, nicht wahr?
Supposing you become
Jetzt stellen Sie sich vor,
the owner of that power, say, or if you have that power within you.
Sie werden zum Besitzer dieser Kraft, Sie haben diese Kraft in sich.
You can also do many things.
Dann können auch Sie viele Dinge tun.
REPORTER: But, nonetheless, I mean,
Trotzdem, ich meine,
if I have an illness I go to see a doctor, he gives me tablets or so on…
wenn ich krank bin, gehe ich zum Arzt und bekomme Tabletten,
I mean, to actually to come and see You
aber zu Ihnen zu kommen,
and You say I’ve got the power within me to cure myself…
und Sie sagen mir, ich habe eine Kraft, um mich zu heilen,
I mean, how do you actually get this power?
also, wie bekommt man diese Kraft denn?
SHRI MATAJI: You see, what happens: when you become realized,
Wenn Sie Ihre Selbstverwirklichung bekommen,
or we become — it’s called twice-born —
oder ihre zweite Geburt,
then you become collectively conscious, you become.
dann werden Sie kollektiv bewusst. Sie werden es.
It is not that I just tell you
Das sage Ich nicht nur,
and it’s a brain treatment or something,
es ist keine Behandlung des Gehirns
or brainwash, that I say,
und keine Gehirnwäsche, dass Ich sage:
“All right, now you have become this and this.”
"Jetzt sind Sie dies und das geworden."
You really become, that you start feeling them —
Sie werden es tatsächlich und beginnen sie zu spüren,
they are centres on your fingertips.
es sind die Energiezentren auf den Fingerspitzen.
REPORTER: So you actually feel them? SHRI MATAJI: On the fingertips.
Man kann sie spüren? Auf den Fingerspitzen.
You can, everyone can feel it very clearly.
Jeder kann das sehr klar spüren.
REPORTER: So this is like a guide, this is the way to diagnose
Das ist also wie ein Wegweiser, der Weg zur Diagnose.
SHRI MATAJI: Diagnosis. You see, you are the doctor,
Ja, Diagnose. Sie sind der Arzt,
you are the diagnosis, you could be patient also.
Sie sind die Diagnose und Sie können auch der Patient sein.
And you are the medicine.
Sie sind die Medizin.
REPORTER: So once you’ve diagnosed what's wrong…
Und wenn ich diagnostiziert habe, was mir fehlt...
SHRI MATAJI: Then you should know how to cure a particular centre.
Dann sollten Sie wissen, wie man ein Energiezentrum heilt.
For example, now, which is the Christ centre? It’s this one.
Zum Beispiel ist das hier das Zentrum von Christus.
These two are Christ centres,
Diese beiden sind Zentren von Christus
in the pituitary and pineal. Now what are the diseases you get?
in der Hirnanhang- und Zirbeldrüse. Sie sind verantwortlich für
All the diseases of the eyes you get out of it.
alle Augenkrankheiten.
Others are possessions.
Außerdem gibt es Besessenheiten,
You see, people are mentally depressed, this, that —
z. B. wenn Leute depressiv sind,
all this is due to the problem of this centre.
das sind alles Probleme auf diesem Zentrum.
There could be ego problems also.
Es können auch Ego-Probleme sein.
People are egoistical, you see, and very bombastic,
Manche Leute sind egoistisch und prahlerisch,
and they try to destroy others with their ego.
und versuchen, andere mit ihrem Ego zu zerstören.
All these problems can be solved if you can awaken Christ within you.
Wenn wir Christus in uns erwecken, kann all das gelöst werden.
Because it’s said that He died for our sins.
Denn es heißt, dass Er für unsere Sünden gestorben ist.
REPORTER: And using this healing method You've got, that actually awakens powers [of healing]
Und mit Ihrer Methode werden Heilkräfte erweckt?
SHRI MATAJI: Yes. You just have to say Lord's prayer before Me
Ja, Sie müssen nur das Vaterunser vor Mir sagen,
and He awakens because I am connected with Him, you see.
und Er wird erweckt, weil Ich mit Ihm verbunden bin.
So when you say something to Me,
Wenn Sie etwas zu Mir sagen,
that connection is just made, and that is awakened,
entsteht diese Verbindung und Er wird erweckt.
and there is ego and superego in your head, which are sucked in,
Dabei werden das Ego und das Superego in Ihrem Kopf aufgesaugt.
means your actions — that is your karmas —
D. h. Ihre Handlungen, also Ihr Karma,
and your sins all are sucked in.
und Ihre Sünden werden aufgesaugt.
Once they are sucked in, this portion opens up.
Wenn das geschieht, öffnet sich diese Stelle.
When this opens up, you get the the Kundalini up.
Und dann kann die Kundalini aufsteigen.
That is, it’s very simple, you know, because it’s all done.
Es ist ganz einfach, denn alles ist bereits vorhanden.
For example, now look at this. To look at this, looks very simple,
Sehen Sie sich beispielsweise das an. Es sieht simpel aus,
but it might be quite complicated inside.
aber vielleicht ist es von innen betrachtet recht kompliziert,
And it has taken years to make it.
und es hat viele Jahre gedauert, es zu entwickeln.
So the whole thing has taken ages to make it. This human body
Genauso hat es Ewigkeiten gedauert, das zu entwickeln. Der Körper
has come out of amoeba to this stage;
des Menschen hat sich von der Amöbe aufwärts entwickelt,
even from matter to this stage. All that is built within you.
aus reiner Materie bis hierhin. Das alles ist in Ihnen angelegt.
Not only that, but what is going to happen to you
Und mehr noch. Was mit Ihnen geschieht,
is also existing within you in your heart; the Spirit.
existiert bereits in Ihrem Herzen: der Spirit.
Now, only thing, that last [ ] breakthrough has to take place.
Jetzt muss nur noch der letzte Durchbruch stattfinden.
That is also built within you, that is sahaja —
Auch das ist in Ihnen angelegt, es ist "sahaja",
means built within you. It is born within you.
es ist angeboren.
Sahaja is “born within”. So it’s all within you.
"Sahaja" heißt "angeboren". Alles ist in Ihnen angelegt.
And just if somebody knows how to do the job,
Wenn nur jemand weiß, wie es geht,
the one who could have capacity…
jemand die Fähigkeit dazu hätte...
Like the Mother Earth has the capacity to sprout the seed.
So wie die Mutter Erde einen Samen sprießen lassen kann.
We can’t do it otherwise, if you do grow, do anything, you can't.
Anders geht es nicht. Wenn Sie wachsen, können Sie nichts dafür tun.
It’s a living process. But the Mother… Mother Earth can help.
Es ist ein lebendiges Geschehen. Aber die Mutter Erde kann helfen.
You put it there and you get it.
Sie stecken den Samen in die Erde und es geschieht.
In the same way, it is supposing I have the capacity, I can do it.
Nehmen wir einmal an, Ich habe die Fähigkeit, Ich kann das tun.
Supposing you get the light tomorrow, you can do it.
Und morgen erfahren Sie das Licht, und Sie können es tun.
You can enlighten another person.
Sie können einen anderen Menschen erleuchten.
One enlightened person can enlighten another person
Jeder erleuchtete Mensch kann einen nächsten erleuchten,
but he has to be enlightened first of all.
aber zuerst muss er erleuchtet werden.
REPORTER: Do You find that, I mean, as You say, I mean,
Wollen Sie damit sagen,
once people have seen You and discovered how it can work,
wenn die Menschen bei Ihnen waren und entdeckt haben, wie es geht,
they can spread the word? SHRI MATAJI: Yes.
dann können Sie es weitergeben? Ja.
REPORTER: But nonetheless You say You met a lot of skeptical people last time.
Trotzdem sagen Sie, letztes Mal waren viele skeptisch.
Do You think that that is the basic problem I mean that…
Glauben Sie, das ist das Hauptproblem? Ich meine,
through this healing process You have
diese Heilkraft, die Sie haben,
could be much more widely used and sort of...
könnte doch viel mehr genutzt werden.
SHRI MATAJI: You see, but I’ve seen people who come for healing,
Wissen Sie, es kamen Leute, um geheilt zu werden,
just get satisfied at that point when they are healed up.
und sie sind zufrieden, sobald sie geheilt sind.
They don’t go further.
Weiter gehen sie aber nicht.
You see you must say that God also has common sense;
Sie müssen verstehen, dass auch Gott mit Verstand vorgeht.
that He would like to only heal people, normally,
Wenn es Ihm nur darum ginge zu heilen,
like we would like to only construct,
wäre es so, als würden wir nur Lampen bauen
improve, or repair those lamps which will give lights, isn’t it?
oder sie verbessern oder reparieren, damit sie leuchten.
So those who are not going to work it out;
Diejenigen, die sich nicht entwickeln möchten,
the interest is less.
stoßen auf weniger Interesse.
But still it works, I mean, it’s compassion,
Aber es funktioniert trotzdem. Es geschieht aus Mitgefühl,
so it cures, people get cured, no doubt.
und zweifellos gibt es eine Heilung.
But out of them I find very few really come to Sahaja Yoga,
Aber nur wenige derjenigen, die kamen, um geheilt zu werden,
who come through healing. But those who have seeking of the Spirit
bleiben in Sahaja Yoga. Während Leute, die den Spirit suchen,
they are a special category of people.
ein besonderer Schlag von Menschen sind.
They are extremely beautiful people
Es sind Menschen von großer innerer Schönheit,
and they are seeking. Maybe they are taking drugs,
und sie suchen. Vielleicht nehmen sie Drogen,
going to wrong gurus, whatever they are doing.
oder gehen zu falschen Gurus. Was auch immer sie tun,
That’s a different point.
das ist etwas anderes.
But they are seekers, basically they are seekers of the truth
Aber sie sind Sucher, Sucher der Wahrheit,
and they are the best people.
und das sind die besten Menschen.
And they are the ones who are meant for Sahaja Yoga,
Und sie sind für Sahaja Yoga gedacht,
not the people who just want their body to be all right.
nicht diejenigen, die nur wollen, dass es ihrem Körper gut geht.
What’s the use of having the body, what are you going to do with it?
Was nützt der Körper? Was tun Sie damit?
You see, this body might have a meaning.
Dieser Körper hat vielleicht eine Bedeutung,
And those who are finding the meaning are the best helped.
und wer diese Bedeutung erkennt, dem kann am besten geholfen werden.
Of course, they get rid of all their maladies
Natürlich werden sie frei von ihre Krankheiten,
and everything that’s… as a by-product.
aber das ist eine Nebenerscheinung.
But that’s the main thing, that’s important.
Aber im Grunde geht es um etwas anderes.
REPORTER: I understand that Your husband, in fact,
Nun ist es so, dass Ihr Ehemann
holds a very eminent position. SHRI MATAJI: Yes, he is.
eine sehr hohe Position hat. Ja, das ist so.
REPORTER: Can You tell me a little bit about that?
Können Sie mir darüber ein wenig erzählen?
SHRI MATAJI: He is elected as Secretary General.
Er wurde zum Generalsekretär gewählt.
REPORTER: Of what exactly?
Wo genau?
SHRI MATAJI: Of one international organization you have,
Eine internationalen Organisation bei Ihnen,
a one agency you have in this country,
eine Institution in Ihrem Land,
called as International Maritime Organization,
die Internationale Seeschifffahrts-Organisation,
which has got 134 nations
der 134 Nationen angehören,
who have elected him. And that’s how we are here.
hat ihn gewählt. Deshalb sind wir hier.
REPORTER: Do You find… I mean, his work
Finden Sie nicht, ich meine...
must be so completely different to Yours.
seine Arbeit muss doch ganz anders sein als Ihre.
SHRI MATAJI: No, it’s quite just the same, I feel,
Nein, für Mich ist das so ziemlich das Gleiche,
because My work only works out how I meet people, isn’t it?
denn Meine Arbeit ist nur möglich, wenn Ich Menschen treffe,
And when I meet the people, I find they like My work.
und wenn Ich sie treffe, merke ich, dass Sie Meine Arbeit mögen.
I help his people also sometimes, you can say,
Manchmal helfe Ich auch seinen Leuten,
for something wrong with them.
wenn etwas nicht in Ordnung ist bei ihnen.
But it never collides with My work at all, I find,
Für Mich kollidiert das überhaupt nicht mit Meiner Arbeit,
because you are so…
weil man so...
you become so loving and affectionate and so tolerant
weil sie einen so liebevoll und herzlich und tolerant macht,
that you just don’t feel anything else.
dass man einfach gar nichts anderes spürt.
It’s very nice to meet new people because…
Es ist toll, neue Leute zu treffen...
Because of him I’ve gone to many communist countries,
Durch ihn konnte Ich in so viele kommunistische Länder reisen.
I visited China and visited Russia…
Ich war in China und in Russland.
All these places I could not have visited.
All diese Orte hätte Ich anders nicht besuchen können.
REPORTER: I think, um…
Ich meine...
I mean, You must have a great deal of difficulty
Sie müssen doch große Schwierigkeiten damit haben,
convincing people that You are a genuine, bona fide
die Menschen zu überzeugen, dass Sie  es wirklich gut meinen.
person, You know, it’s a little bit dangerous.
Es ist doch ein wenig gefährlich, oder?
Do You find that there is, um, problems with people who are
Haben Sie denn Probleme mit Leuten, also...
extreme, sort of extreme people who are... ?
Leuten, die irgendwie extrem sind?
SHRI MATAJI: You see, it depends on what country you are.
SHRI M: Das kommt ganz auf das Land an, in dem man ist.
Say, in India it’s not difficult at all, because they understand this,
In Indien etwa ist es ganz einfach,  dort versteht man diese Dinge.
They know, they have had an education on this,
Sie wissen das und haben gelernt,
that the one who awakens the Kundalini is the real person.
dass jemand, der die Kundalini erweckt, eine ehrliche Person ist.
You see, they can see the rising of the Kundalini,
Sie können sehen, wie die Kundalini aufsteigt,
they can see the pulsation of the Kundalini,
sie sehen das Pulsieren der Kundalini,
they can feel the pulsation here.
und sie können es hier fühlen.
It’s all told them, so they know about it.
Das alles wurde ihnen gesagt, und sie wissen das.
I don’t have to work out with them.
Mit ihnen habe Ich keine Arbeit.
But if otherwise the…
Aber sonst,
most of the seekers in other countries also have
auch die meisten Sucher in anderen Ländern
come to right conclusions, because they have had a very bad time.
haben die richtigen Schlüsse aus ihrem schweren Leben gezogen.
So they have come to right conclusions, I mean it’s not so difficult.
Sie haben sich richtig entschieden. Es ist nicht so schwer.
But of course, you know,
Aber natürlich
that if there’s too much mental projection, then rather difficult.
ist es schwierig, wenn zu viel mental projiziert wird.
But it doesn’t matter.
Das macht aber nichts.
REPORTER: Are there fakes in this country?
Gibt es falsche Gurus hier bei uns?
SHRI MATAJI: So many. Most of them are.
Ja viele. Die meisten sind falsch.
REPORTER: I mean, they must be Your biggest headache,
REP: Das muss für Sie doch das größte Problem sein,
I should think, maybe.
denke ich mir.
SHRI MATAJI: They are not only Mine but of all the seekers.
Sie sind nicht nur mein Problem, sondern das der Sucher.
And that’s very true.
Das ist sehr wahr.
They really ruin seekers. I’ve known people, they make money,
Sie zerstören die Sucher. Ich kenne solche Leute. Sie nehmen ihr Geld,
put these people out of jobs, out of their lives,
die Leute verlieren ihre Arbeit und werden aus der Bahn geworfen.
make them abnormal, sick like cabbages,
Sie werden zu anormalen, kranken Menschen.
they take away… the children are ruined…it's horrible.
Sie nehmen....die Kinder nehmen Schaden...es ist schrecklich.
Some of them get epilepsy, some of them get cancer…
Manche erkranken an Epilepsie, andere an Krebs,
all kinds of diseases. Some people become blind.
an allen möglichen Krankheiten. Manche werden blind.
They all punish them-
Sie werden alle bestraft.
REPORTER: You don’t in fact charge anything, do You?
Sie nehmen kein Geld für Ihre Arbeit, oder?
SHRI MATAJI: No no no. No no.
Nein, nein, nein. Nein, nein.
REPORTER: Then how is, Your trips round the country,
Wie ist es dann mit Ihren Reisen überall hin,
to different countries and around Britain and so on,
in andere Länder und in ganz England usw.,
how are they actually funded then?
wer bezahlt das eigentlich alles?
SHRI MATAJI: You see, it is mostly funded by My husband.
Das meiste bezahlt mein Mann.
Mostly he’s a generous man.
Er ist meistens sehr großzügig.
REPORTER: That’s lucky, isn’t it!
Das ist aber ein Glück, oder?
SHRI MATAJI: He’s generous.
Er ist großzügig.
Otherwise also I have My some income of My own.
Aber Ich habe auch ein wenig eigenes Einkommen.
REPORTER: How much would You estimate
Was schätzen Sie,
that You spend trying to spread the word, a year?
wie viel Sie jährlich ausgeben, um Ihre Botschaft zu verbreiten?
SHRI MATAJI: Well, I can't say that, I’m not good at accounting,
Das kann ich nicht sagen. In Geldfragen bin Ich nicht gut,
but I would say that when I travel,
aber wenn Ich reise,
for example, supposing I go to any other country,
beispielsweise ins Ausland,
sometimes Sahaja Yogis think that I should not pay
möchten die Sahaja Yogis manchmal nicht, dass Ich bezahle,
for their salvation, you see.
für Ihr Heil.
So out of their self-respect they pay My traveling sometimes,
Deshalb zahlen sie Meine Reisen manchmal aus Selbstrespekt.
but they don’t pay Me but to the travel agency or something they,
Aber sie geben das Geld nicht Mir, sondern dem Reisebüro. Oder sie
buy tickets for Me at the most, that’s all.
kaufen die Tickets für Mich, das ist alles.
But not much, it’s not much per year.
Aber es ist nicht viel im Jahr.
REPORTER: Where have You traveled this year?
Wohin gingen Ihre Reisen dieses Jahr?
SHRI MATAJI: Now, this year, let’s start.
Dieses Jahr... fangen wir an:
When… where did I go, can you…?
Wann - wo war Ich überall, könnt ihr es sagen?
Now, I came from America…
Also, Ich kam aus Amerika,
Geneva, Austria, Belgium,
Genf, Österreich, Belgien,
Spain, Portugal, France,
Spanien, Portugal, Frankreich,
Germany… Russia, I went to Russia, Uzbekistan.
Deutschland... Russland. Ich war in Russland, in Usbekistan,
REPORTER: And this is all this year, is it?
Und alles dieses Jahr, oder?
SHRI MATAJI: Yes, this year, yes... REPORTER: You must be worn out.
Ja. Sie müssen erschöpft sein.
SHRI MATAJI: Do I look that? Now I’m sixty. I’m sixty now.
Sehe Ich so aus? Ich bin jetzt sechzig.
REPORTER: Really? SHRI MATAJI: Yes, I'm sixty years of age, really.
Wirklich? Ja wirklich, Ich bin sechzig.
REPORTER: You don’t look sixty years old at all.
Sie sehen kein bisschen so aus wie sechzig.
REPORTER: How did it all start for You then,
Wie fing denn alles an bei Ihnen,
I mean, right at the beginning?
also ganz am Anfang?
Well, say, I mean, most people know very little
Also, die meisten Leute wissen ja nur wenig
about this sort of thing, me included.
über diese Dinge, ich eingeschlossen.
But how did that actually all start in the beginning for You?
Wie hat das denn eigentlich alles angefangen für Sie?
SHRI MATAJI: You see, actually I was aware of it
Wissen Sie, Ich wusste das
from My very childhood, as you are aware, say, for example,
von frühester Kindheit an, so wie Sie zum Beispiel wissen,
you are aware you are a human being. In the same way I was aware.
dass Sie ein Mensch sind. So war auch mir bewusst, wer Ich bin.
I was absolutely aware of Me, and My mission,
Ich war mir meiner selbst und meiner Aufgabe bewusst.
and what I… why I’m here, what I am.
Ich wusste, warum Ich hier bin und wer Ich bin.
Everything  I was aware of from My very childhood.
Das alles war mir schon als Kind bewusst.
But I was working out how to do it in en masse happening.
Aber Ich wollte herausfinden, wie es en masse geschehen kann.
It would be for the masses.
Es sollte für die Massen sein.
My father himself was a realized soul
Mein Vater selbst war eine realisierte Seele,
and he was a member of the Parliament and Assembly in those days,
und er war damals Mitglied des Parlaments und der Versammlung,
and he was the only Indian to be elected.
er war der einzige gewählte Inder.
Indian Christian to be elected, I should say.
Oder vielmehr der einzige indische Christ.
My brother also is a Minister of… what is he Minister of?
Mein Bruder ist auch ein Minister für... wofür ist er Minister?
Communications and something else.
Kommunikation und noch etwas.
REPORTER: So, I mean, I suppose in India,
Also, ich denke in Indien
I mean, that it’s not as difficult to actually, um
dort ist es doch nicht so schwierig,
It’s only when You start traveling abroad?
Schwierig ist es nur, wenn Sie ins Ausland gehen.
SHRI MATAJI: Oh, Indians understand much better.
Oh, die Inder verstehen das viel besser.
REPORTER: That’s what I was saying.
Ja, das meine ich.
SHRI MATAJI: But abroad is the problem. Because, you see, they…
Aber im Ausland ist es schwierig, denn wissen Sie,
they are naive, they don’t know.
die Leute sind naiv, es fehlt ihnen an Wissen.
You see, Christ’s life was only for four years.
Christus hat nur vier Jahre lang gelebt, wissen Sie,
He couldn’t tell them much about it; about the Holy Ghost.
Er konnte ihnen nicht viel darüber sagen, über den Heiligen Geist.
It’s all a mystery, you see.
Es ist alles ein Mysterium.
The Christianity could not give that, because they never went
Das Christentum konnte das den Menschen nicht geben, denn man hatte
into the search of it, you see, the deeper of it.
niemals danach gesucht, nach tieferen Erfahrungen.
Just reading Bible, telling some sort of an interpretation
Nur die Bibel lesen und eine Art Interpretation dazu zu geben,
doesn’t give you anything.
das bringt nichts.
So the second birth part of it they didn’t work out.
Um den Aspekt der zweiten Geburt hat man sich nicht gekümmert.
And that’s why I find people got lost more,
Deshalb meine Ich, sind die Menschen auf größere Irrwege geraten,
because of these gurus coming, giving them some ideas, this, that…
denn diese Gurus, die kamen, setzten ihnen Dinge in den Kopf.
And they sort of are hypnotized also to a great extent.
Viele wurden auch so was wie hypnotisiert.
All these people are hypnotized, brainwashed,
All diese Leute sind hypnotisiert und hatten eine Gehirnwäsche,
then they, some of them went into drugs.
und einige begannen auch, Drogen zu nehmen.
You see, so many things, they are all self-destroying.
Es gibt so viele Dinge, damit zerstören sich die Menschen selbst.
That’s how I found people very much confused, very much confused.
Deshalb traf Ich viele Menschen sehr verwirrt an.
Of course, the people in India
Natürlich, die Leute in Indien,
say, for example, of this entrepreneur,
zum Beispiel dieser Unternehmer,
He knows I am a saint.
er weiß, dass Ich eine Heilige bin.
So he treats Me like a saint, it’s a very big thing,
Und er behandelt mich auch so. Das ist etwas sehr Großes,
and then he'll come to receive Me and…
er kommt zu Mir, um Mich zu empfangen.
that even the Prime Minister of India,
Sogar der indische Premierminister,
Mr. Lal Bahadur Shastri,  My husband was his secretary,
Lal Bahadur Shastri - mein Mann war sein Sekretär -
but he used to come and see Me often, in the car, you see.
aber er kam oft zu Mir, im Auto, wissen Sie.
So in India it’s a… saint is higher than all kings
In Indien ist ein Heiliger mehr als alle Könige
and everyone put together, you see.
und alle zusammengenommen, wissen Sie.
So they know how to respect a saint, even for popularity.
Man weiß,  wie man einen Heiligen behandelt - auch für den gute Ruf.
REPORTER: Do You find that, I mean… to call Yourself a saint…
Finden Sie, ich meine, Sie bezeichnen sich als eine Heilige,
do You find that the people in England…
finden Sie, dass die Menschen in England..
SHRI MATAJI: They are not so much.
Es gibt nicht so viele.
REPORTER: You know, they're not…they're not quite as keen…
Sie sind nicht so sehr darauf aus,
SHRI MATAJI: (unclear...) the saints, I think.
(unklar...) Heilige, meine Ich.
No, they care more for politicians.
Nein, ihnen sind die Politiker wichtiger.
REPORTER: That’s right, that’s right.
Genau.
I mean, do You find, You know, sort of…
Haben Sie denn das Gefühl,
I mean, You are little bit insulted by them sometimes?
fühlen Sie sich manchmal beleidigt von ihnen?
SHRI MATAJI: Aah, it’s all right.
Ach, das ist in Ordnung.
REPORTER: I mean, You firmly believe in what You do, obviously, and
Sie glauben ja offensichtlich sehr fest an das, was Sie tun.
it must seem incredible to You when other people [ignore?] it.
Es muss ganz unglaublich für Sie sein, wenn andere das ignorieren.
SHRI MATAJI: It’s all right. You see, after all they are children,
Es ist in Ordnung. Sie sind schließlich Kinder,
they don’t understand. That’s all I can say.
sie verstehen es nicht. Mehr kann Ich dazu nicht sagen.
Because they are still children in spiritual life, you see.
Was Spiritualität angeht, sind sie noch Kinder,
But they are not going to crucify Me this time, isn’t it?
aber diesmal werden sie Mich nicht kreuzigen, nicht wahr?
So it’s all right.
Also ist alles in Ordnung.
REPORTER: Now, when You make these trips
Wenn Sie diese Reisen machen
to towns like Northampton and so on,
in Städte wie Northhampton und so weiter,
You got several people with You.
sind immer einige Leute bei Ihnen.
Does this team come with You every time?
Begleitet Sie dieses Team jedes Mal?
SHRI MATAJI: No, they are from this place, some of them are now
Nein, sie sind jetzt von hier,
and some of them are there also. Of course all the others
und natürlich sind auch andere sind dabei.
they have come from Australia.
Manche sind aus Australien.
And we have an ashram in South London.
Und wir haben einen Ashram in Südlondon.
So they are staying there, so they just came around here.
Sie wohnen dort und sind einfach hergekommen.
And these two are from -
Diese beiden hier sind von ...,
he’s working in London, he is also there.
er hier arbeitet in London.
And these three gentlemen are from Bedford. He is from Bristol.
Und diese drei kommen aus Bedford. Er ist aus Bristol.
REPORTER: Oh I see. SHRI MATAJI: But there is nothing like that,
Ich verstehe. Aber wir haben kein
is that a team or anything.
festes Team oder so etwas.
Anybody who feels like can come around if they’re free, because…
Jeder, der möchte, kann kommen, wenn er Zeit hat, denn...
REPORTER: So anyone who is available for You, to help…
Also jeder, der helfen kann...
SHRI MATAJI: Yes, they can just to help Me,
Ja, sie können Mir einfach helfen,
because if it’s a big group and all that, so they can help Me.
denn wenn es viele sind, können sie mir auch helfen.
REPORTER: I see, all right, I see.
Ach so, ich verstehe.
Well, thanks very much for Your time.
Vielen Dank, dass Sie sich Zeit genommen haben.
SHRI MATAJI: Thank you very much. But I think you should ask
Vielen Dank. Aber ich finde, Sie sollten noch
one more question if you can, say, about Kundalini,
eine Frage stellen, wenn das geht, über die Kundalini,
because those who have read about Kundalini
denn wer etwas über die Kundalini gelesen hat,
would be interested to know.
ist daran interessiert.
Is that, is said that, you see, lots of books
Es gibt viele Bücher, in denen
have been written about Kundalini,
über die Kundalini geschrieben ist,
that it’s very dangerous, it is very (this thing?), and all that.
dass es sehr gefährlich ist und so weiter.
But it is not at all.
Aber das ist überhaupt nicht so.
You see, thousands of people I’ve given realization. Thousands.
Ich habe Tausenden von Leuten die Selbstverwirklichung gegeben.
It has never put anybody into danger at all.
Und niemals ist jemand dadurch in Gefahr gekommen.
But those who are naïve, those who are unholy persons,
Aber naive und gottlose Menschen,
who have no idea of a spiritual life, you see,
die keine Ahnung von Spiritualität haben,
if they try tricks, you see,
wenn sie es mit Tricks versuchen,
like sex, you see, through sex and all that nonsense,
wie mit Sex und all diesem Unsinn,
then it feels insulted, and then there are problems.
dann ist die Kundalini beleidigt.
REPORTER: How can it be dangerous then?
Wie kann es dann gefährlich sein?
SHRI MATAJI: Beg your pardon? REPORTER: How, You said, it can be dangerous
Wie bitte? Wie kann sie gefährlich sein,
if it's not used properly?
wenn sie nicht richtig behandelt wird?
SHRI MATAJI: You see, like we could say that
Schauen Sie, man könnte sagen,
if I don’t know this instrument and I put My hand into something,
wenn ich dieses Gerät nicht kenne, es anfasse und mich daran
I may get a burning, but it doesn’t mean this is dangerous,
verbrenne, heißt das nicht, dass das Gerät gefährlich ist.
that is because I don’t know how to work it…
Es liegt an meiner Unwissenheit.
REPORTER:That is basic, I mean, if you don’t understand it's
Ja klar, wenn man nichts davon versteht,
like putting your finger in an electric light socket...…
ist das, als ob man den Finger in die Steckdose steckte.
But they try to do it
Aber sie versuchen es trotzdem,
and then they try to write books about it.
und dann versuchen sie, Bücher darüber zu schreiben.
It’s something surprising, isn’t it?
Das ist doch erstaunlich, oder?
I haven’t written any book so far.
Ich habe bisher noch keine Bücher geschrieben.
REPORTER: So, that’s obviously, You know,
Ja, klar,
sort of the thing you've got to try and make clear to people.
Sie müssen versuchen, das den Leuten zu erklären.
SHRI MATAJI: Yes, you have to. And then, you see,
Ja, das muss man. Und dann,
when you get realization, you automatically become righteous,
nach der Selbstverwirklichung verhält man sich automatisch richtig.
I don’t have to tell you “Become righteous.”
Ich muss nicht sagen: "Seid anständig",
Because the religion is enlightened within you.
denn Ihre innere Religion wird erleuchtet.
You automatically become. I don’t tell you that “You don’t drink,”
Man wird es automatisch. Ich sage nicht: "Trinken Sie nicht",
you just don’t drink, because you don’t enjoy it any more.
Sie trinken einfach nicht mehr, weil Sie es nicht mehr genießen,
You don’t smoke, because you just don’t enjoy it; don’t take drugs.
Sie rauchen nicht, weil es nicht schmeckt, Sie nehmen keine Drogen.
Just you just don’t do it because it’s all enlightened,
Sie tun das einfach nicht, weil alles in Ihnen erleuchtet ist
because a new priority has come.
und Sie eine neue Priorität haben.
Like if there’s light in this room, suddenly you start seeing
Wenn dieser Raum beleuchtet ist, dann beginnen Sie zu sehen,
where’s the position of everything,
wo alles steht.
and you know, if you walk this way, you’ll be hit.
Und Sie wissen, wenn ich hier lang gehe, stoße ich mich an.
In the same way, enlightenment means that
Genauso bedeutet Erleuchtung,
automatically you become righteous.
dass man sich automatisch richtig verhält.
REPORTER: What is Your success rate in full for healing people?
Wie hoch ist Ihre Erfolgsrate bei der Heilung von Leuten?
SHRI MATAJI: What is?… REPORTER: What is Your success rate
Bitte? Ihre Erfolgsrate
for healing people who come to see You?
im Heilen?
SHRI MATAJI: Success? REPORTER: Successful or have helped them.
Erfolg? Wie erfolgreich konnten Sie helfen?
REPORTER: How many times do You actually heal people
Wie viele der Menschen, die zu Ihnen kommen,
compared to the number of people who come to see You?
werden von Ihnen geheilt?
SHRI MATAJI: Oh, some people just come, for ten minutes is sufficient.
Oh, bei manchen reichen 10 Minuten aus.
Our president Sanjiva Reddy, the first president,
Unser Präsident Sanjiva Reddy, der erste Präsident,
he was coming from England… America.
er kam aus England... nein, Amerika zurück.
His operation had failed, he was just in a very bad shape.
Seine Operation war erfolglos und er war in schlechtem Zustand.
I just went to see him
Ich ging zu ihm,
and he didn’t know I was Mataji, but he knew Me as Mrs. Shrivastav.
er kannte Mich nicht als "Mataji", sondern als "Frau Srivastava."
And suddenly our High Commissioner told him,
Da sagte unser Hoher Kommissar plötzlich zu ihm:
“This is Mataji Nirmala Devi.”
"Das ist Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi."
So his wife said, “I’ve heard You have cured so many people,
Da sagte seine Frau: "Ich habe gehört, Sie heilen viele Menschen,
so just cure my husband.”
bitte heilen Sie meinen Mann."
I put My hand only for ten minutes, you’ll be surprised.
Ich legte Meine Hand nur 10 Minuten lang auf ihn,
He was just, then — he got it.
und da war er schon - er hatte es bekommen.
REPORTER: This can happen every time
Kann das jedes Mal so sein,
when You get somebody come to see You?
wenn jemand zu Ihnen kommt?
SHRI MATAJI: Not always. Some people take more time,
Nicht immer, bei manchen dauert es länger,
some people take less time.
bei anderen geht es schneller.
It depends on if they are complicated,
Je nachdem, wie kompliziert sie sind,
you see, they take more time, some of them do.
brauchen manche länger, andere weniger lang.
You see, for example, supposing I have to break through, now.
Angenommen, Ich muss hier durchbrechen,
And if you are just there, you will out.
wenn Ich kurz davor bin, bin Ich gleich draußen.
REPORTER: Are there some people You just simply can’t heal?
Gibt es Menschen, die Sie einfach nicht heilen können?
SHRI MATAJI: Some people… I don’t know, but, you see…
Manche... Ich weiß nicht, aber...
I don’t know, I don’t remember of someone
Ich weiß nicht, Ich kann mich an niemanden erinnern,
who came to Me and was not healed so far.
der zu Mir kam und nicht geheilt wurde.
Some might have been, I don’t know.
Vielleicht gab es manche, ich weiß nicht.
But those who came, you see, assiduously —
Aber wenn jemand wirklich konsequent gekommen ist -
I don’t think, isn’t it?
Ich glaube, da war niemand, oder?
As far as I remember, I should say.
Jedenfalls soweit ich Mich erinnern kann.
REPORTER: Yeah, You've done quite a lot.
Ja, Sie haben wirklich viel getan.
SHRI MATAJI: You see, there are so many I have, it has happened,
Wissen Sie, da waren So viele, mit denen es so war,
even these people are healing, you see.
selbst diese Leute hier können heilen.
So there’s no end to it. Imagine,
Es geht immer so weiter. Stellen Sie sich vor,
one person is Me, I can remember for Myself,
Ich bin nur eine Person und kann Mich erinnern, was bei Mir war,
but there are so many they are healing, and
aber es gibt so viele, die heilen,
I just forget about it, I just don’t remember.
und ich vergesse einfach vieles, Ich erinnere Mich nicht.
Once I had gone to a program, I was just sitting.
Einmal war Ich bei einem Treffen, Ich hatte Mich gerade gesetzt,
One gentleman came, he just touched My feet.
da kam ein Herr und berührte Meine Füße.
I said, “Who are you?” He said, “You forgot me?”
Ich fragte: "Wer bist du", und er sagte: "Wissen Sie das nicht mehr?"
I said, “Why?” I said, “I’m sorry.”
Ich sagte: "Nein, tut Mir leid, warum?"
He said, “I’m the father of such and such girl,
Er sagte: "Ich bin der Vater von diesem Mädchen,
whom You cured in two minutes time,
das Sie in nur 2 Minuten geheilt haben,
who was going to die, and this and that in the hospital.”
das beinahe gestorben wäre im Krankenhaus."
I said, “Really?”
"Wirklich", sagte Ich.
I tried to remember, I said, “Who was this?” you see.
Ich versuchte Mich zu erinnern, wer das war.
Then with very great difficulty I remembered,
Und nur mit Mühe konnte Ich mich erinnern,
because it was so quick.
weil es so schnell gegangen war.
I had gone to see somebody else
Ich war eigentlich zu jemand anderem gekommen,
and on My way back he caught hold of Me.
und auf Meinem Weg zurück, sprach er mich an.
And there she was. She was cured in such a quick manner
Und da war das Mädchen. Sie wurde so schnell geheilt,
that I'd forgotten all about it. REPORTER: Really?
dass Ich schon alles vergessen hatte. Wirklich?
Well, I suppose, the proof is in the pudding, isn’t it?
Ja, ich denke, man muss es wohl selbst ausprobieren, richtig?
SHRI MATAJI: Yes. And moreover, what I’m saying
Ja, und außerdem sagte Ich ja,
it is not important. What is important is to become Spirit.
das ist nicht wichtig. Wichtig ist, dass Sie zum Spirit werden.
Healing is not important.
Heilen ist nicht wichtig.
You see, because everyone has to die in any case, isn’t it?
Schließlich müssen wir alle einmal sterben, ist es nicht so?
What is important  that you have to become the Spirit.
Wichtig ist, dass Sie der Spirit werden müssen.
That is. And then you heal others.
Darum geht es. Und dann können Sie andere heilen.
Not only yourself, you can heal yourself and heal others also.
Nicht nur sich selbst. Sie können sich selbst und andere heilen.
REPORTER: All right, very good... Well, as I say,
Ok, sehr gut. Also dann
thank You, thank You for Your time.
vielen Dank, dass Sie hier waren.
SHRI MATAJI: Many incurable diseases you can put,
Sie können viele unheilbare Krankheiten nehmen,
but that’s not the main job, I think.
aber das ist nicht die Hauptaufgabe.
REPORTER: Yes. I think that’s probably the thing
Ja, ich denke, das ist vielleicht die Sache,
that a lot of people are most interested in.
um die es den meisten Leuten geht.
SHRI MATAJI: I agree, yes. YOGI: Excuse me, Mother.
Ja, das stimmt. YOGI: Entschuldige Mutter,
When you asked me[UNCLEAR] in Paris, and Mother took it very well,
als ich in Paris gefragt wurde (unklar), und Mutter nahm das gut auf,
but they described Her as a man.
aber es wurde gesagt, Sie sei ein Mann.
[YOGINI SPEAKING]
[YOGINI SPRICHT]
SHRI MATAJI: What is she…
Was sagt sie?
REPORTER: I think you are speaking to the wrong person.
Ich glaube, Sie sprechen nicht zur richtigen Person.
YOGI: I’m getting confused.
YOGI: Das verwirrt mich.
SHRI MATAJI: What is it? What is it?
Worum geht es?
[YOGINI SPEAKING]
[YOGINI SPRICHT]
SHRI MATAJI: Yeah. REPORTER: This is in fact…
Ja.  Das ist tatsächlich…
SHRI MATAJI: Ah, I remember that.
Oh, Ich erinnere mich.
And he also said I’m a He, you see, put My photograph.
Er sagte auch, Ich sei ein Er, und nahm mein Foto.
And they referred to Me as a He, you see, [UNCLEAR].
Und Sie sprachen von Mir als von einem Er (unklar),
REPORTER: In fact, this would be the first article we've ever run on You, so....
Das wäre tatsächlich der erste Artikel, den wir über Sie machen, also...
(Yogi apologizing)SHRI MATAJI: This is [unclear].
(Yogi entschuldigt sich)(unverständlich)
REPORTER: That’s all right, that’s all right.
Kein Problem.
It often happens, actually.
Das kommt öfters vor.
SHRI MATAJI: It happens. I’ve seen, there have been
Ja, Ich habe
so many things - like Me, also, as you said, I am just…
vieles erlebt. Auch Ich, wie Sie bereits sagten,
sometimes I don’t remember all… REPORTER: That’s right.
erinnere Mich manchmal nicht. Ja, richtig.
SHRI MATAJI: All right. So…
Also gut.
REPORTER: Can I take just two more pictures?
Darf ich bitte noch zwei Fotos machen?
SHRI MATAJI: Yes yes, please, please go ahead.
Ja natürlich.
PHOTOGRAPHER: Actually, if You could close Your hands,
Fotograf: Wenn Sie Ihre Hände falten könnten,
so… You know, which is normally…do you mind if I move this?
so wie normalerweise... Darf ich das hier verschieben?
SHRI MATAJI: As you say. REPORTER: Sometimes a problem.
Wie Sie möchten. Das ist manchmal schwierig.
SHRI MATAJI: Our style is like this. Is this all right?
Wir machen es eigentlich so. Ist das in Ordnung?
SHRI MATAJI: You can ask
Sie können auch darum bitten,
to put their hands towards My photograph also.
dass sie ihre Hände zum Foto halten.
My photograph has vibrations.
Mein Foto hat Vibrationen.
You see, they have got realization from My photograph.
Sie haben die Selbstverwirklichung durch Mein Foto bekommen.
Yes, really, they have been cured from My photograph.
Sie wurden auch geheilt durch Mein Foto.
REPORTER: That’s incredible, isn’t it? SHRI MATAJI: Yes, that's it,
Das ist unglaublich! Ja, wirklich.
That’s what I was speaking, it's going to help,
Das ist, wovon Ich gesprochen habe. Es hilft.
Sahaj is going to help all of them.
Sahaj wird ihnen allen helfen.
REPORTER: So the more of them we get, a thousand more pictures we have…
Je mehr wir also haben, wenn wir nochmals tausend haben.,,
SHRI MATAJI: Yes, the pictures. These people (unclear)
Ja. Diese Leute (unverständlich)
something like [unclear] photograph.
(unverständlich) so etwas wie... Foto.
Not only as photograph but just cure people, we have seen.
Es heilt die Menschen, das habe Ich erlebt.
And first time I went to Australia,
Als Ich zum ersten Mal in Australien war,
there was big  [unclear]
gab es ein großes (unverständlich)
What happened, that a relation of a very big man in that industry
Und ein Verwandter eines wichtigen Industriellen
was [unclear].
war (unverständlich)
And a lady, one of the Sahaja Yoginis,
Eine Sahaja Yogini
so she said that, “I can’t (...unclear...),
sagte, Sie könne nicht (unverständlich)
so let's put a photograph" and (unclear).
also lasst uns ein Foto aufstellen (unverständlich).
[UNCLEAR]
(Unverständlich)
Not only that, not only that,
Aber nicht nur das.
but the patient (unclear, was perfectly all right?)
Der Patient wurde (völlig gesund?)
And that’s how they gave it and that’s how
So haben sie es gemacht.
the photograph [works out? unclear].
Und so hat das Foto (unverständlich)
One of them, you see, is another journalist who is a realized soul.
Einer von ihnen ist ein Journalist, der die Selbstverwirklichung hat.
REPORTER: Oh I see. It’s the question of, You know,
Aha, das Problem ist doch,
making people see, isn’t it starting I suppose once....
es denn Menschen klar zu machen. Wenn es einmal anfängt....
SHRI MATAJI: I think, I think so. Otherwise [unclear].
Ja, ja, das denke Ich auch. Sonst (unverständlich)
REPORTER: [unclear]
[unverständlich]
SHRI MATAJI: [Unclear] responsibility
[unverständlich] Verantwortung
[unclear] for everyone.
[unverständlich] für jeden.
REPORTER: [unclear] SHRI MATAJI: Isn’t it?
[unverständlich] Nicht wahr?
After all, newspaper should give some good news also.
Eine Zeitung sollte schließlich auch etwas Positives berichten.
May God bless you.
Gott segne Sie.
[unclear]. You are [unclear]. It’s all right.
[unverständlich] Sie sind  [unverständlich]. Gut.
All right. It was very beautiful.
Gut. Das war sehr schön.
We can give this address. Will you please?
Wir können die Adresse zeigen.
And you tell them about [unclear].
Sprechen sie darüber.  [unverständlich]
Tell them about [unclear]. [Can you ... unclear] ?
Sprechen Sie darüber.  [unverständlich]
[unclear Douglas is genius?].
[unverständlich - Douglas ist ein Genie?]
I want [unclear] anyway, he wants to [unclear].
[unverständlich]
He’s a genius. He’s a genius.
Er ist ein Genie.
It's the truth.
Es ist wahr.
He got into speed and I also got to got into speed with him,
Er wurde immer schneller, und Ich dann auch zusammen mit ihm.
I said, “Let Me talk fast.”
Ich bat darum, dass Ich schnell sprechen darf.
All right? Now, thank you for the cameraman.
Danke. Danke auch an den Kameramann.
“This team follows You”, he said come.
"Das Team wird Ihnen folgen", sagte er.